So that's Johnny Depp, of course.
هذا جوني ديب الممثل الأمريكى.
And that's Johnny Depp's shoulder.
وهذا هو كتف جوني ديب
And that's Johnny Depp's famous shoulder tattoo.
وهذا وشم كتف الممثل جوني ديب الشهير
Some of you might know that, in 1990,
ربما بعضكم يعلم أنه في عام 1990 ،
Depp got engaged to Winona Ryder,
خطب جوني ديب الممثلة وايونا رايدر
and he had tattooed on his right shoulder
وقد قام بوشم عبارة على كتفه حينها تقول
"Winona forever."
"وايونا للأبد"
And then three years later --
وبعد ثلاث سنوات لاحقاً
which in fairness, kind of is forever by Hollywood standards --
وكأنه نظام متبع في هوليوود
they broke up,
إنفصلا الثنائي،
and Johnny went and got a little bit of repair work done.
وقد عزم جوني ديب على محاولة إصلاح ما وشمه على كتفه.
And now his shoulder says, "Wino forever."
ليحول العبارة على كتفه إلى " وينو للأبد "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So like Johnny Depp,
ومثل جوني ديب،
and like 25 percent of Americans
حوالى 25% من الأمريكين
between the ages of 16 and 50,
بين عمر 16 - 50،
I have a tattoo.
لدي أنا أيضاً وشم
I first started thinking about getting it in my mid-20s,
حيث بدأت أفكر في الوشم على جسدي في منتصف العشرينات من عمري
but I deliberately waited a really long time.
ولكنى إنتظرت بصورة متعمدة مدة طويلة لكي أرسمه.
Because we all know people
لأننا جميعا نعلم أناس
who have gotten tattoos when they were 17
وضعوا أوشام على أجسادهم في عمر ال17
or 19 or 23
أو 19 أو 23
and regretted it by the time they were 30.
وندموا عليه في عمر ال 30 .
That didn't happen to me.
لكن هذا لم يحدث لي
I got my tattoo when I was 29,
لقد رسمت وشمي في عمر 29 ،
and I regretted it instantly.
وندمت على ذلك على الفور.
And by "regretted it,"
و " ندمت بسببه "
I mean that I stepped outside of the tattoo place --
أعني ما أن خرجت من محل الأوشمة --
this is just a couple miles from here
والذي هو على بعد ميلين من هنا
down on the Lower East Side --
في منطقة الجنوب الشرقي
and I had a massive emotional meltdown in broad daylight
حتى حدث لي إنهيار عصبي تام في وضح النهار
on the corner of East Broadway and Canal Street.
بتقاطع شارع القناة وشارع شرق برودواي ( مدينة نيويورك )
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Which is a great place to do it because nobody cares.
الذى يعتبر أفضل مكان يمكن أن تضع وشمك لأنه لا أحد يهتم بما يحدث.
And then I went home that night, and I had an even larger emotional meltdown,
ومن ثم ذهبت إلى منزلي، لكي أصاب بإنهيارعصبي بصورة أكبر مما حدث لي في الصباح،
which I'll say more about in a minute.
والذي سوف أتحدث عنه لاحقاً
And this was all actually quite shocking to me,
وكان هذا الموقف صادماً بالنسبة لي،
because prior to this moment,
لأنه تبعاً لتلك اللحظة،
I had prided myself
كانت لدى نظرة إحترام لنفسي
on having absolutely no regrets.
لأنني لم أندم على شيء مطلقاً.
I made a lot of mistakes
قمت بالكثير من الأخطاء
and dumb decisions, of course.
وقرارات خاطئة، بالطبع.
I do that hourly.
أقوم بذلك بصفة مستمرة.
But I had always felt like, look, you know,
لكن كنت دوما أشعر، وكأننى،
I made the best choice I could make
قمت بأفضل شيء يمكن عمله حينها
given who I was then,
تبعا لما كنت عليه حينها،
given the information I had on hand.
وتبعا للمعلومات التي كنت أعرفها حينها.
I learned a lesson from it.
لكن تعلمت شيئاً من ذلك.
It somehow got me to where I am in life right now.
إن هذا المبدأ كان سبباً لما أنا عليه الآن.
And okay, I wouldn't change it.
ولن أغيره.
In other words, I had drunk our great cultural Kool-Aid about regret,
بعبارة أخرى، كنت فى حالة فخر بثقافتنا العظيمة بالندم كإستمتاع الطفل الصغير بشرابه.
which is that lamenting things that occurred in the past
فيما يتعلق بالأسى نتيجة أشياء حدثت لى فى الماضى
is an absolute waste of time,
ألا وهى بالتأكيد مضيعة للوقت،
that we should always look forward and not backward,
حيث أن الإنسان يتوجب عليه دوما أن ينظر إلى الأمام لا إلى الخلف،
and that one of the noblest and best things we can do
الذى يعتبر أنبل وأفضل الأشياء التى يمكننا عملها حيال أنفسنا
is strive to live a life free of regrets.
هو أن نسعى نحو الأمام فى الحياة بدون ندم.
This idea is nicely captured by this quote:
إن هذه الفكرة اللطيفة يمكن توضيحها بالعبارة المقتبسة التالية :
"Things without all remedy
" إن الأشياء التي لا يمكن العودة إليها وتغيرها
should be without regard;
لايجب أن نندم عليها،
what's done is done."
فما تم فعله قد مضى بلا عودة. "
And it seems like kind of an admirable philosophy at first --
وتبدو أنها نوع من فلسفة رائعة لأول وهلة --
something we might all agree to sign onto ...
شيئ من الممكن أن نتفق عليه جميعاً ...
until I tell you who said it.
حتى أن أفصح لكم من هو قائل العبارة.
Right, so this is Lady MacBeth
حسناً إنها السيدة ماكبث ( أقصر رواية مسرحية لوليام شكسبير )
basically telling her husband to stop being such a wuss
وقد قالت ذلك لزوجها كى يكف عن كونه جبان
for feeling bad about murdering people.
لإحساسه المزعج حيال قتل الناس.
And as it happens, Shakespeare was onto something here,
وعندما قالت هذا " كان شكسبير يقصد شيئاً هنا "
as he generally was.
وهو عادة هكذا.
Because the inability to experience regret
لأن عدم القدرة على إختبار الندم
is actually one of the diagnostic characteristics
هو فى الحقيقة عادة يكون أحد أعراض
of sociopaths.
المختلين نفسياً.
It's also, by the way, a characteristic of certain kinds of brain damage.
كما أنه بالمناسبة، يعتبر عدم الشعور بالندم عرض من أعراض التلف الدماغي
So people who have damage
فالأشخاص الذين لديهم عطب
to their orbital frontal cortex
في القشرة المدارية الأمامية
seem to be unable to feel regret
لا يبدو أنهم قابلين للشعور بالندم
in the face of even obviously very poor decisions.
حتى في مواجهة أتعس وأتفه القرارات.
So if, in fact, you want to live a life free of regret,
لذلك في الحقيقة، إذا أردت أن تعيش حياة خالية من الندم،
there is an option open to you.
هناك إختيار مفتوح أمامك.
It's called a lobotomy.
وتسمى " لبوتومى " ( عملية جراحية فى القشرة العقلية )
But if you want to be fully functional
ولكن إن أردت أن تكون فعْالاً حقاً
and fully human
وإنسان بكل معانى الكلمة
and fully humane,
وإنسانٌ دمث الخلق،
I think you need to learn to live, not without regret, but with it.
أعتقد أنك تحتاج أن تتعلم كيفية العيش، ليس بدون ندم، بل كيفية العيش به.
So let's start off by defining some terms.
حسنا دعونا أولا نُعرف بعض المفاهيم
What is regret?
ما هو الندم؟
Regret is the emotion we experience
ان الندم هو شعور نشعر به
when we think that our present situation
عندما نظن أن موقفنا الحالى
could be better or happier
كان ممكن أن يكون في مكان أفضل وأكثر سعادة
if we had done something different in the past.
لو أننا فعلنا شيئاً مختلفاً فى الماضى.
So in other words, regret requires two things.
بعبارة أخرى، الندم يتطلب أمرين.
It requires, first of all, agency -- we had to make a decision in the first place.
يتطلب أولاً، فكر مُنظم أو قوة -- علينا أن نتخذ قرار فى البداية.
And second of all, it requires imagination.
والأمر الثاني، يتطلب خيال.
We need to be able to imagine going back and making a different choice,
لأننا نحتاج أن نتخيل أنفسنا نعود إلى الماضي لكي نقوم بقرار مختلف عن القرار الاول،
and then we need to be able to kind of spool this imaginary record forward
ومن ثم نحتاج أن نكون قادرين على تدوير هذه المخيلة وتحريكها للأمام
and imagine how things would be playing out in our present.
ونتخيل أمورنا فى الحاضر كيف ستكون بعد هذا القرار التخيلى.
And in fact, the more we have of either of these things --
في الحقيقة، كلما كنا قادرين على فعل أى من هذين الأمرين ..
the more agency and the more imagination
كلما كنا أكثر قدرة على التغيير وقدرة على التخيل
with respect to a given regret,
مع إحترام الندم الذي يساورنا،
the more acute that regret will be.
كلما كان الندم حاداً وقاسياً.
So let's say for instance
لنقل على سبيل المثال
that you're on your way to your best friend's wedding
أنك على طريقك للذهاب إلى عرس أعز أصدقائك
and you're trying to get to the airport and you're stuck in terrible traffic,
وتحاول جاهداً أن تصل المطار ولكن الطريق مزدحم،
and you finally arrive at your gate
وتصل فى النهاية إلى بوابتك
and you've missed your flight.
وقد أقلعت طائرتك.
You're going to experience more regret in that situation
وسوف تندم كثيراً على تصرفك في تلك الحالة
if you missed your flight by three minutes
إن فاتتك الرحلة بسبب تأخيرك ثلاث دقائق
than if you missed it by 20.
أكثر من ندمك إن فوتها لتأخرك بعشرين دقيقة.
Why?
لماذا؟
Well because, if you miss your flight by three minutes,
لأنه إن فاتتك الرحلة بسبب ثلاث دقائق
it is painfully easy to imagine
فمن السهل أن تتألم فى التخيل
that you could have made different decisions
أنك كان يمكن أن تقوم بخيارات أخرى
that would have led to a better outcome.
كان يمكن أن تقود إلى نتائج أفضل.
"I should have taken the bridge and not the tunnel.
مثل " كان يجب أن أسلك الجسر عوضاً عن النفق
I should have gone through that yellow light."
كان يجب أن أتجاوز الإشارة الصفراء "
These are the classic conditions that create regret.
هذه هى حالات طبيعية تولد الندم
We feel regret when we think we are responsible
نحن نشعر بالندم عندما نظن أننا مسؤولون
for a decision that came out badly,
عن قرار كانت نتائجه سلبية،
but almost came out well.
لكن وقتها تقريباً كان صواب.
Now within that framework,
الآن خلال هذا السياق،
we can obviously experience regret about a lot of different things.
يمكننا أن نشعر بالندم حيال أشياء كثيرة مختلفة.
This session today is about behavioral economics.
هذه الفقرة من المؤتمر عن التصرفات الإقتصادية
And most of what we know about regret
ومعظم ما نعرفه عن الندم
comes to us out of that domain.
يأتي من هذا النطاق.
We have a vast body of literature
لدينا ثقافة واسعة
on consumer and financial decisions
عن الشراء والقرارات المالية.
and the regrets associated with them --
والندم مرتبط بهما ..
buyer's remorse, basically.
مثل ندم الشاري على سبيل المثال.
But then finally, it occurred to some researchers to step back
ولكن في النهاية تبين لبعض الباحثين أنهم أخذوا خطوة للوراء
and say, well okay, but overall,
وأخذوا يتسائلون أنه، في الخلاصة،
what do we regret most in life?
ما هو أكثر شيء نندم عليه في هذه الحياة؟
Here's what the answers turn out to look like.
وهاكم ما توصلت إليه الإجابات على ذلك السؤال.
So top six regrets --
حسناً أكثر 6 أمور نندم عليها ..
the things we regret most in life:
الأشياء التى نندم عليها في هذه الحياة :
Number one by far, education.
كان التعليم في المرتبة الأولى.
33 percent of all of our regrets
إذ أن 33 % من ندمنا
pertain to decisions we made about education.
ترجع إلى قرارات إتخذناها في حقل التعليم
We wish we'd gotten more of it.
فجميعنا يتمنى لو أنه حصل على تعليم أكثر
We wish we'd taken better advantage of the education that we did have.
ونتمنى لو أننا إستفدنا بصورة أكبر وأفضل من تعليمنا الذى حصلنا عليه.
We wish we'd chosen to study a different topic.
نتمنى لو أننا إخترنا تخصص دراسي مختلف.
Others very high on our list of regrets
والأمور الأخرى التي تتصدر القائمة فيما يخص الندم
include career, romance, parenting,
منها التخصص الوظيفي والعلاقات العاطفية والأبوة والأمومة،
various decisions and choices about our sense of self
عدة قرارات وخيارات متعلقة بإحساسنا بأنفسنا ومواقفنا
and how we spend our leisure time --
وكيف نقضي وقت فراغنا وهواياتنا ..
or actually more specifically,
بعبارة أوضح وأدق،
how we fail to spend our leisure time.
كيف نفشل في قضاء وقت فراغنا.
The remaining regrets
أما باقي قائمة الندم
pertain to these things:
فهي تضم التالي :
finance, family issues unrelated to romance or parenting,
الحالة المادية، المشاكل العائلية التي لا تتعلق بالإختيار العاطفي أو التربية،
health, friends,
الصحة، الأصدقاء،
spirituality and community.
الروحانيات، المجتمع.
So in other words, we know most of what we know about regret
لذا بعبارة أخرى، معظم ما نعرفه فى معرفتنا بالندم
by the study of finance.
من دراسة الوضع الإقتصادي.
But it turns out, when you look overall at what people regret in life,
لكن تبين، عندما ننظر نظرة عامة إلى ما يندم عليه البشر فى الحياة،
you know what, our financial decisions don't even rank.
أتعلمون، قرارتنا الإقتصادية لا تؤخذ فى وجه الإعتبار.
They account for less than three percent of our total regrets.
إنها لا تحوز أكثر من 3% من الأمور التي نندم عليها.
So if you're sitting there stressing
حسناً إن كنت تجلس متوجساً حيال
about large cap versus small cap,
حدودك العظمى مع حدودك الصغرى ( ميزانيتك الصغيرة )،
or company A versus company B,
أو شركة ( أ ) ضد شركة ( ب )،
or should you buy the Subaru or the Prius,
أو هل يتوجب أن تشترى سيارة سوباروا أو بريوس،
you know what, let it go.
أتعلمون دعكم من هذا.
Odds are, you're not going to care in five years.
إحتمالات الأمر، هى أنكم لن تهتموا لهذا القرار خلال خمس سنوات من إتخاذه.
But for these things that we actually do really care about
لكن بالنسبة لتلك القرارات التى نهتم بها فعلياً
and do experience profound regret around,
والتى نختبر ندم عميق حيالها،
what does that experience feel like?
هل يمكن وصف هذا الشعور؟
We all know the short answer.
الجميع يعرف الإجابة الأسهل لهذا السؤال.
It feels terrible. Regret feels awful.
إنه شعور مؤلم. فالندم مقيت.
But it turns out that regret feels awful
لكن يتضح لنا أن الإحساس بالندم مخيف
in four very specific and consistent ways.
فى أربع مراحل محددة جداً ومتسقة.
So the first consistent component of regret
العنصر الأول الدائم من شعور الندم
is basically denial.
هو الإنكار.
When I went home that night after getting my tattoo,
عندما عدت إلى المنزل في تلك الليلة بعد أن وشمت نفسى،
I basically stayed up all night.
بقيت ساهرة طيلة الليل.
And for the first several hours,
وفي الساعات الأولى،
there was exactly one thought in my head.
كانت تدور فكرة واحدة في مخيلتي
And the thought was,
وتلك الفكرة كانت،
"Make it go away!"
" أزيليه ! "
This is an unbelievably primitive emotional response.
هذه إستجابة بسيطة للمشاعر لا تصدق.
I mean, it's right up there with, "I want my mommy!"
أعني .. إنها تتموضع مع " أريد والدتي ! "
We're not trying to solve the problem.
فنحن لا نحاول بهذا التصرف حل تلك المشكلة.
We're not trying to understand how the problem came about.
ولا نحاول أن نفهم كيف حدثت المشكلة.
We just want it to vanish.
كل ما نريده هو أن تختفي تلك المشكلة
The second characteristic component of regret
والعنصر الثاني من شعور الندم
is a sense of bewilderment.
هو شعور بالإرتباك والحيرة.
So the other thing I thought about there in my bedroom that night
إن الأمر الثاني الذي واجهته حينها في غرفة نومي
was, "How could I have done that?
كان قولى " كيف أمكنني القيام بذلك ؟ ..
What was I thinking?"
ما الذي كنت أفكر به ؟ "
This real sense of alienation
إنه شعور حقيقي بالإغتراب
from the part of us that made a decision we regret.
عن جزء من شخصيتنا التي قامت بإتخاذ ذلك القرار الذى نندم عليه.
We can't identify with that part.
فلا يمكننا " التعرف " على هذا الجزء.
We don't understand that part.
ولا يمكننا فهم ذلك الجزء منا.
And we certainly don't have any empathy for that part --
وحتماً لا نتعاطف مع هذا الجزء من أنفسنا ..
which explains the third consistent component of regret,
وهذا ما يفسر وجود العنصر الثالث من الندم،
which is an intense desire to punish ourselves.
وهو الشعور برغبة في معاقبة أنفسنا.
That's why, in the face of our regret,
وهذا سبب، فى مواجهة ندمنا،
the thing we consistently say is, "I could have kicked myself."
الشيئ الذى نردده على الدوام " توبيخ للنفس على فعل ما "
The fourth component here
و العنصر الرابع
is that regret is what psychologists call perseverative.
هو ذلك الندم الذى يسميه علماء النفس المواظبة.
To perseverate means to focus obsessively and repeatedly
أي أن تواظب على التركيز بصورة شديدة ومتكررة
on the exact same thing.
على نفس الشيء فقط.
Now the effect of perseveration
وتأثير المواظبة
is to basically take these first three components of regret
هو بصورة أساسية أخذ العناصر الثلاثة الأولى للندم
and put them on an infinite loop.
ووضعهم معاً فى حلقة كبيرة غير محدودة.
So it's not that I sat there in my bedroom that night,
لذا لا يعنى أننى جلست في غرفتي تلك الليلة،
thinking, "Make it go away."
متفكرة " أزيلية "
It's that I sat there and I thought,
بل أنه يعني أننى جلست هناك وقلت،
"Make it go away. Make it go away.
" أزيليه، أزيليه.
Make it go away. Make it go away."
أزيليه. أزيليه "
So if you look at the psychological literature,
حسناً إن نظرتم إلى هذا التفسير النفسى،
these are the four consistent defining components of regret.
سترون أن هذه ال4 مكونات الدائمة التى تحدد مفهوم الندم.
But I want to suggest that there's also a fifth one.
ولكني أريد أن أقترح وجود مكون خامس
And I think of this
وأفكر به على
as a kind of existential wake-up call.
أنه نوع من نداء وجودي إعتراني .
That night in my apartment,
حينها في شقتي تلك الليلة،
after I got done kicking myself and so forth,
بعد أن وبخت نفسى كثيراً،
I lay in bed for a long time,
إستلقيت في الفراش طويلاً،
and I thought about skin grafts.
وكنت أفكر في ترقيع الجلد.
And then I thought about how,
ومن ثم قلت في نفسي،
much as travel insurance doesn't cover acts of God,
كم من وسائل تأمين كتأمين السفر لا تغطى أعمال الله،
probably my health insurance did not cover acts of idiocy.
فمن المؤكد أن تأمينى الصحي لا يغطي التصرفات الغبية.
In point of fact, no insurance covers acts of idiocy.
فى واقع الأمر، لا يوجد تأمين ضد التصرفات الغبية.
The whole point of acts of idiocy
أن القصد من التصرفات الغبية
is that they leave you totally uninsured;
هي أنها تتركك تحس بعدم الأمان على الإطلاق،
they leave you exposed to the world
فالتصرفات الغبية تجعلك مكشوف الظهر أمام العالم
and exposed to your own vulnerability and fallibility
وتكشف طبيعتك الضعيفة القابلة للوقوع فى الخطيئة
in face of, frankly, a fairly indifferent universe.
أمام هذا العالم القاسى الغير مبالي بك صراحةً.
This is obviously an incredibly painful experience.
في الحقيقة هذه تجربة مؤلمة صعبة التصديق.
And I think it's particularly painful for us now in the West
وأعتقد أنها تحديداً باتت مؤلمة لنا نحن في الغرب
in the grips of what I sometimes think of
حيث إننا نعيش أحياناً فيما أسميه
as a Control-Z culture --
ثقافة CTRL+Z ( السيطرة على الحاسوب )
Control-Z like the computer command,
فالحاسوب لديه ميزة CTRL+Z
undo.
وهي ميزة التراجع عن تنفيذ أمر ما.
We're incredibly used to not having to face
نحن غير مستعدون على الإطلاق لمواجهة
life's hard realities, in a certain sense.
حقائق الحياة القاسية، في إدراك يقينى مؤكد.
We think we can throw money at the problem
نظن أننا يمكننا أن نعالج مشكلة ما بضخ الأموال فيها
or throw technology at the problem --
أو يإستخدام تكنوجيا معينة ..
we can undo and unfriend
نظن أننا يمكننا أن نتراجع عن أمر معين وفك الصداقات
and unfollow.
وعدم التتبع ( كما في تويتر والبرامج الأخرى )
And the problem is that there are certain things that happen in life
ولكن المشكلة أن هناك أحداث معينة تحدث فى الحياة
that we desperately want to change
نكون فى أمس الإحتياج أن نغيرها
and we cannot.
ولكننا لا نستطيع ذلك.
Sometimes instead of Control-Z,
فأحيانا كثيرة نحن لا نملك الخاصية CTRL+Z
we actually have zero control.
في الحقيقة لا نملك أي تحكم بأي شيء.
And for those of us who are control freaks and perfectionists --
وفيما يخص القائمين على إدارة وتحكم الأخرين كما يريدون والراغبين فى الكمال
and I know where of I speak --
وأنا أعى تماماً أين أتحدث ..
this is really hard,
إنه لأمر صعب للغاية،
because we want to do everything ourselves and we want to do it right.
لأننا نريد أن نقوم بكل شيء بأنفسنا وتبعا لقراراتنا ونريد أن نقوم به بصورة صحيحة.
Now there is a case to be made
وهناك حالة يجب أن تؤخذ بعين الإعتبار
that control freaks and perfectionists should not get tattoos,
أن مهوسي التحكم والراغبين فى الكمال لايجب على الإطلاق أن يحصلوا على " وشم "،
and I'm going to return to that point in a few minutes.
وسأعود لهذه النقطة خلال دقائق.
But first I want to say
ولكن بداية علي أن أقول
that the intensity and persistence
أن شدة وحدة وإستمرارية
with which we experience these emotional components of regret
أفكارنا ومشاعرنا التى تصاحب وتتبع إحساس الندم
is obviously going to vary
بالتأكيد سوف تتباين وتتمايز
depending on the specific thing that we're feeling regretful about.
تبعاً للأمر المعين الذي نشعر بالندم حياله.
So for instance, here's one of my favorite
حسنا على سبيل المثال .. هذا أحد أمثلتي المفضلة
automatic generators of regret in modern life.
مولدات ندم أتوماتيكية في الحياة الحديثة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Text: Relpy to all.
المسمى : الرد للجميع !
And the amazing thing
والشيئ المدهش
about this really insidious technological innovation
فيما يخص هذا الإبداع التكنولوجى المتفشى
is that even just with this one thing,
إنه حتى مع هذا الشيئ الواحد،
we can experience a huge range of regret.
يمكننا ان نواجه طيفاً واسعاً من الندم.
You can accidentally hit "reply all" to an email
فمن الممكن أن تضغط بالخطأ على زر" الرد للجميع " عندما تريد الرد على بريد ألكتروني
and torpedo a relationship.
فتهدم علاقة.
Or you can just have an incredibly embarrassing day at work.
أو تواجه يوماً محرجاً في العمل
Or you can have your last day at work.
أو أن يكون اليوم الأخير في عملك.
And this doesn't even touch
وهذا حتى لا يمس
on the really profound regrets of a life.
الندم العميق الذي يعترينا في الحياة.
Because of course, sometimes we do make decisions
لأنه بالطبع، أحيانا نقوم بقرارات
that have irrevocable and terrible consequences,
لا رجعة فيها وعواقبها رهيبة،
either for our own or for other people's
سواء علي أنفسنا أو على أناس آخرون
health and happiness and livelihoods,
خاصة بصحتهم أو سعادتهم أو طريقة المكسب فى الحياة،
and in the very worst case scenario, even their lives.
وفي الحالات الأسوء .. حتى فى حياة هؤلاء أنفسهم.
Now obviously, those kinds of regrets
الآن كما يتجلى لنا ... تلك الأنواع من الندم
are incredibly piercing and enduring.
تترك جروح غائرة دائمة صعبة العلاج.
I mean, even the stupid "reply all" regrets
أعني حتى الندم الغبي جراء " الرد على الجميع "
can leave us in a fit of excruciating agony for days.
يمكن أن يجعلنا نغرق في ندم وعذاب مبرح لعدة أيام.
So how are we supposed to live with this?
فكيف إذا يمكننا التعايش مع هذا؟
I want to suggest that there's three things
أريد أن أقترح ثلاثة أشياء
that help us to make our peace with regret.
تساعدنا على التأقلم مع الندم.
And the first of these
وأولها
is to take some comfort in its universality.
هو الوعي بأن الندم شيء طبيعى ويصيب الجميع.
If you Google regret and tattoo,
إن قمتم بالبحث عن كلمة ( الوشم + الندم )،
you will get 11.5 million hits.
سوف تحصلون على 11.5 مليون نتيجة بحث
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The FDA estimates
فقد قدرت إدارة الغذاء والدواء الأمريكية
that of all the Americans who have tattoos,
أنه من بين الأمريكيين الذي وشموا أنفسهم،
17 percent of us regret getting them.
17% يندمون على ذلك.
That is Johnny Depp and me
من مثلي ومثل جوني ديب
and our seven million friends.
و 7 مليون صديق آخر.
And that's just regret about tattoos.
وهذا فقط الندم حيال الوشم.
We are all in this together.
نحن جميعاً معاً في هذا الشعور.
The second way that we can help make our peace with regret
والأمر الثاني الذي يجعلنا نتقبل ونتأقلم مع الندم
is to laugh at ourselves.
هو أن نسخر من أنفسنا.
Now in my case, this really wasn't a problem,
في حالتي لم يكن الأمر بهذه الصعوبة،
because it's actually very easy to laugh at yourself
لأنه من السهل جداً أن تسخروا من أنفسكم
when you're 29 years old and you want your mommy
خاصة وأني في 29 من عمري وأريد أمى كى أبكى لها
because you don't like your new tattoo.
لأنني لم أحب وشمي الجديد.
But it might seem like a kind of cruel or glib suggestion
لكن يبدو الأمر كأنه نوع من القسوة أو إقتراح عفوى
when it comes to these more profound regrets.
عندما يأتي الأمر لندم أكثر شدة وعمق.
I don't think that's the case though.
لكني لا أظن أن الأمر بهذه السهولة.
All of us who've experienced regret
جميع الذين مروا بخبرة ندم
that contains real pain and real grief
كانت تتضمن آلام وحزن حقيقي
understand that humor and even black humor
يدركون جيداً أن الفكاهة وحتى الكوميديا السوداء
plays a crucial role in helping us survive.
تلعب دوراً أساسياً في جعلنا نتجاوز الأزمة.
It connects the poles of our lives back together,
إنها تعيد إستجماع قوى حياتنا معاً كما كانت فى السابق،
the positive and the negative,
الإيجابية والسلبية،
and it sends a little current of life back into us.
فتعيد تيار الإستعداد للحياة في عقولنا وأجسادنا كما كانت من فبل.
The third way that I think we can help make our peace with regret
والأمر الثالث الذي أظن أنه يساعد على التاقلم مع الندم
is through the passage of time,
هو بمرور الزمن،
which, as we know, heals all wounds --
الذي كما نعرف أنه دواء لكل داء..
except for tattoos, which are permanent.
حتماً بإستثناء الأوشمة، فهي دائمة إلى الأبد.
So it's been several years
حسناً .. لقد مضت عدة سنوات
since I got my own tattoo.
منذ أن قمت بوشم جسدي.
And do you guys just want to see it?
هل تريدون رؤية هذا الوشم؟
All right.
حسناً
Actually, you know what, I should warn you,
في الحقيقة .. يجب أن أحذركم،
you're going to be disappointed.
سوف تخيب توقعاتكم عنه
Because it's actually not that hideous.
لأنه ليس بهذه البشاعة.
I didn't tattoo Marilyn Manson's face
فلم أوشم صورة وجه " مارلين مانسون " ( مغنية أمريكية )
on some indiscreet part of myself or something.
في مكان خفي على جسدي أو ما شابه.
When other people see my tattoo,
عندما يرى الآخرون وشمي،
for the most part they like how it looks.
معظمهم يعجبون بما يبدو عليه.
It's just that I don't like how it looks.
إنما أنا لا أحب شكله.
And as I said earlier, I'm a perfectionist.
وكما قلت مسبقاً " إنني ساعية نحو الكمال "
But I'll let you see it anyway.
لكنى سوف أريكم إياه على أية حال.
This is my tattoo.
هذا هو وشمي
I can guess what some of you are thinking.
يمكنني أن أتوقع ما يدور في خلد البعض منكم
So let me reassure you about something.
حسناً دعوني أوكد لكم شيئاً
Some of your own regrets
بعض الأمور التي نندم عليها
are also not as ugly as you think they are.
ليست قبيحة كما نظن أنها كذلك.
I got this tattoo
لقد رسمت هذا الوشم
because I spent most of my 20s
لأنني قضيت معظم فترة العشرينات من عمري
living outside the country and traveling.
أعيش خارج بلدى مسافرةً.
And when I came and settled in New York afterward,
وعندما عدت وإستقريت في نيويورك لاحقاً،
I was worried that I would forget
كنت قلقة من أن أنسى
some of the most important lessons that I learned during that time.
بعض من أهم الدروس التي تعلمتها خلال تجوالي.
Specifically the two things I learned about myself
وخاصة الأمرين اللذان عرفتهما عن نفسي
that I most didn't want to forget
واللذان لا أريد أن أنساهما على الإطلاق
was how important it felt to keep exploring
عن أهمية الشعور بمتعة وهدف الإستكشاف
and, simultaneously, how important it is
بالموازاة مع أهمية
to somehow keep an eye on your own true north.
إبقاء نظرة على طريقك الخاص فى الحياة ( True north ).
And what I loved about this image of the compass
وما أحببته حيال صورة هذه البوصلة ( صورتى عن نفسى )
was that I felt like it encapsulated both of these ideas
كانت أننى شعرت وكأنها تُعبر عن كل من هاتين الفكرتين
in one simple image.
من خلال صورة واحدة.
And I thought it might serve as a kind of permanent mnemonic device.
وقلت إنها ربما تمثل لي كجهاز تذكري دائم بذلك.
Well it did.
وقد كانت كذلك.
But it turns out, it doesn't remind me of the thing I thought it would;
لكن تبين، أنها لا تذكرني بالأمر كما تخيلت أنها ستفعل،
it reminds me constantly of something else instead.
بل إنها تذكرني دائماً بأمر آخر
It actually reminds me
إنها في الحقيقة تذكرني
of the most important lesson regret can teach us,
بأهم درس يمكن أن نتعلمه من الندم،
which is also one of the most important lessons life teaches us.
وهو أيضاً أهم درس في هذه الحياة
And ironically, I think it's probably the single most important thing
ولسخرية الأمر أعتقد ربما أنه الشيء الواحد الأهم
I possibly could have tattooed onto my body --
الذى كان يجب أن أوشمه على جسدي ..
partly as a writer,
بصفتي كاتبة،
but also just as a human being.
لكن أيضاً بصفتي إنسانة.
Here's the thing,
وهاكم هذا الشيء،
if we have goals
إن كنا نملك أهدافاً
and dreams,
وأحلاماً،
and we want to do our best,
ونريد أن نبذل قصارى جهدنا،
and if we love people
وإن كنا قد وقعنا في غرام أشخاص
and we don't want to hurt them or lose them,
ولا نريد أن نؤذى مشاعرهم أو نخسرهم،
we should feel pain when things go wrong.
علينا أن نشعر حقاً بالألم حينما تسير الأمور على نحو سيء.
The point isn't to live without any regrets.
فالفكرة هي أن لا نعيش بدون " ندم ".
The point is to not hate ourselves for having them.
الفكرة هى أن لا نكره أنفسنا لأننا إختارنا وأحببنا هؤلاء الناس لنعيش معهم.
The lesson that I ultimately learned from my tattoo
الدرس الحقيقي فى النهاية الذي تعلمته من وشمي
and that I want to leave you with today
وأريد أن أنقله لكم اليوم
is this:
وهو :
We need to learn to love
علينا أن نتعلم كيف نحب
the flawed, imperfect things
نقائص الشخصية، الأشياء الغير مثالية
that we create
التي صنعناها بأنفسنا
and to forgive ourselves for creating them.
وأن نسامح أنفسنا حيال قيامنا بذلك وصناعتنا إياها.
Regret doesn't remind us that we did badly.
الندم لا يذكرنا بما قمنا به بصورة خاطئة
It reminds us that we know we can do better.
ولكنه يذكرننا دائماً أنه يمكننا القيام بأفضل من ذلك.
Thank you.
شكراًَ لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)